<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Vicissitudes progress, with its convoy through the counties of Essex, Kent, Surrey, Sussex, and Middlesex, to Westminster and to London. By way of premonstration.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 44 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A95903</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing V336</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E452_5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R203899</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863682</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863682</idno>
            <idno type="VID">115893</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A95903)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 115893)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 72:E452[5])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Vicissitudes progress, with its convoy through the counties of Essex, Kent, Surrey, Sussex, and Middlesex, to Westminster and to London. By way of premonstration.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Laurence Chapman, and are to be sold at his shop, next door to the Fountain Tavern in the Strand, near the Savoy,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1648.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The words "Essex, .. Surrey," and "Sussex, and Middlesex," are bracketed together on title page.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "July 11th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Essex (England) --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Kent (England) --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Surrey (England) --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sussex (England) --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Westminster (London, England) --  History --  17th century.</term>
               <term>London (England) --  History --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Middlesex (England) --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:115893:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Viciſſitudes Progreſs, WITH Its Convoy through the COUNTIES OF <hi>Eſſex, Kent, Surrey, Suſſex,</hi> AND <hi>Middleſex,</hi> To <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> and to <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By way of Premonſtration.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>1 Pet. 2.17.</bibl> Fear God, Honor the King.</q>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <bibl>Deut. 17.15.</bibl> Thou ſhalt in any wiſe ſet a King over thee, whom the Lord thy God ſhall chooſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <bibl>Verſe 16.</bibl> But he ſhall not multiply horſes to himſelf, nor cauſe the people to return to Egypt.</p>
               <p>
                  <bibl>Verſe 17.</bibl> Neither ſhall he multiply wives to himſelf, that his heart turn not away: Neither ſhall he greatly multiply to himſelf ſilver and gold.</p>
               <p>
                  <bibl>Verſe 18</bibl> And it ſhall be when he ſitteth upon the Throne of his Kingdom, that he ſhall write him a copy of this Law in a book.</p>
               <p>
                  <bibl>Verſe 19.</bibl> And it ſhall be with him, and he ſhall read therein all the days of his life, that he may learn to fear the Lord his God.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Laurence Chapman,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop, next door to the Fountain Tavern in the Strand, near the Savoy. 1648.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:115893:2"/>
            <head>Viciſſitudes Progreſs: WITH Its Convoy through the Counties of <hi>Eſſex, Kent, Surrey, Suſſex,</hi> and <hi>Middleſex,</hi> to <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter</hi> and to <hi>London.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He mutation of things cauſe oblivion; yet Viciſſitude ſeems to bring new things into the world: But there is no new thing under the Sun, That which hath been, is, and that which is, will be hereafter; onely by reaſon of the mutability of mens mindes, we think thoſe things to be new which we have forgotten to be before: All things de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend, and mount again by changes, ſo as in revolution of time, we receive that for new and good, which was a little before thruſt out as evil, and unſufferable: Such mutations cauſe Diviſions, Factions, Alteration in Religion, change of Government, and ſtrange Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutations in States, Cities, Kingdoms and Empires. Men natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally ſeek after Novelties, and ſo they deſire Eaſe and Liberty; any tye of Obedience is burthenſom, therefore are not long con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent in any condition, neither with a King, nor without a King; will be ſick for a Parliament, and ſick of a Parliament; complain of defects in Governors, yet caſt off all Government: The deſires of men are violent, whirled about, and hurryed after Change with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out conſideration; and their Concupiſcence reſtleſs, not reſtrained by Conſcience, Law nor Puniſhment: though Conſcience check within, and the Magiſtrate curb without, Conſcience is ſmothered, and Magiſtracy trampled in the duſt; God is rejected in his own Ordinance.</p>
            <p>Magiſtracy is Gods Ordinance; the Office and Authority of the Magiſtrate is of Divine Right under the Law, and under the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel;
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:115893:2"/>a ſtamp of Divine power is put upon it, Magiſtrates are ſtiled by Gods own Name, <hi>I have ſaid ye are gods:</hi> they are furniſhed with Authority from God, and bear his perſon, are in his ſtead, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained to be <hi>a terror to the evil, and a praiſe to them that do well:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 13.1, 3.</note> The Magiſtrate is <hi>the miniſter of God, to execute wrath upon him that doth evil;</hi> to this end God hath given Authority to the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate to make penal Laws, and to execute the penalties againſt the offenders, according to the offence; and to ſuch Laws Chriſt requires men to be obedient,
<note place="margin">Rom. 13 5. 1 Pet. 2.15.</note> 
               <hi>Submit to every Ordinance of man for the Lords ſake (ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, for conſcience ſake) whether it be to the King as Supreme, or unto Governors or Rulers ſent by him,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>For ſo is the will of God:</hi> But the Magiſtrate muſt not command any thing contrary to Gods Word; for then we muſt rather ſuffer then obey: Nor is the Magiſtrate to bring clear Texts of Scripture for every particular Command. Where no clear Text forbids, we are bound to ſubmit in all things tending to Government, Civil and Eccleſiaſtical.</p>
            <p>There is diverſity in Magiſtracy, <hi>The King as Supreme, and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernors ſent by him,</hi> &amp;c. a Kings Authority is derivative, Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors or Kings have ſole Rule: where there is abſolute Monarchy, there Will is a Law; as it was in <hi>Caldea, Perſia,</hi> &amp;c. but Kings and Parliaments govern together, where there is mixt Monarchy, and a free People, as once it was in <hi>France,</hi> and is ſtill in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland</hi> (by Gods bleſſing) and in theſe Kingdoms Parliaments (as to Governments) have the chief place of Magiſtracy, yet ſtill the King is Supreme, as King; but Kings Act by their Counſel: Now Parliaments are not ordained only to be the Kings great Councel, but are the full Repreſentative Body of the People, intruſted with all their Rights, and is part of the Regal Power; for the King is ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually in Parliament, though he be perſonally abſent; it is the higheſt Court of Juſtice, a mean between the King and People, to judge or ballaſs between Incroaching Prerogative, and Inſulting Liberty: Parliament onely is Judge, conſiſting of <hi>King, Lords and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons;</hi> not the King, nor the People, Parliaments being inveſted in all Rights belonging to the Subject, are bound to uphold them, they cannot without perjury, and Traytors to Poſterities, give away the Peoples Intereſt, Nor may the People, without extreme ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude and baſeneſs, but maintain Parliaments therein, with hazard
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:115893:3"/>of Life and Eſtate: Men in City and Country, Trade, Traffique, moyl and toyl, as Moles in the earth; Why? to leave Eſtates to their Children: and will you ſell their Freedom by deſerting a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, and ſo leave your Children Bond-ſlaves, not able to ſay this or that is mine, but the Kings, or his to whom He ſhall give it?</p>
            <p>Parliaments (as I ſaid) are intruſted with all the Rights of the Subjects, ſo they have part of the Regal power ſtampt upon their Authority; therefore they muſt give to Ceſar his due, and to the People their dues: <hi>Kings are nurſing fathers,</hi> Protectors of their People, Defendors of their Lives, Rights and Liberties, therefore Kings: What Kings are above the People, is originally from the People, they being inſtituted and choſen by the People for defence, ſecurity and commodity: The people are alſo for ſuch protection, to yield to Kings, willing, loyal and chearful obedience and ſubje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. <hi>That which makes is greater then that which is made, but the People make Kings, no King can make a People;</hi> therefore the ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the People, and a Kingdom, is to be preferred before the Honor of a King.</p>
            <p>It is true, there is Honor, Supremacy and Prerogative belongs as Right to a King, to ſome more, and to ſome leſs, while he is a King; but if he be a Tyrant, and ſeek to deſtroy what he ought to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, What Honor is due, and by whom? I expect an Anſwer: In the mean time, I dare boldly ſay, That the Parliament of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> at this day are willing to give to their King, and to His, as to any of his Progenitors, all His Juſt Rights and Honor; provided His Majeſty endeavor the Right of Patronage, Defence and Secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the Peoples Rights: The Parliament muſt not give the Peoples Intereſt to the King, Nor may the People ſell the Rights of their Poſterities for a morſel of meat, except they will be as prophane <hi>Eſau,</hi> who ſold his Birthright for a meaſs of pottage, curſed to poſterities.</p>
            <p>But the great Queſtion is, <hi>What is Right?</hi> The Law will decide that Controverſie; the People ask but what their Forefathers en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed, and what they bought with the greateſt price: If Law may take place, the Controverſie is quickly ended: Law is the Rule of Juſtice, and Juſtice is the end of the Law; take away the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the Law, and Juſtice hath no foundation: but if Will, not
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:115893:3"/>Law, muſt be Judge on either party, <hi>England</hi> is in a ſad and deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable condition, it is a ſymptome of inevitable ruine to King and People. The King and the People have both one Law to be their Rule, one God to fear and ſerve, one Judge, and one Throne of Judgement where both muſt appear, and there will be no reſpect of perſon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>: It were wiſdom to conſider what anſwer muſt be given, Who ſhall then give account of the wrong done? and for the blood of the ſlain, which cryes, and cryes loud from the earth to heaven, in all parts of His Majeſties three Kingdoms?</p>
            <p>And who but His Majeſty (next under God) can ſtop thoſe ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guine ſhowers, and binde up the bleeding veins of his people? It can no way be done but by the eſtabliſhing of our Laws, ſecuring Religion, priviledges of Parliament, and liberties of the People; by this means the King, his Succeſſors and the people (by Gods bleſſing) ſhall be Cemented together inſeparable, ſecured from future breakings out; His Majeſty being to them, as the heart in the Body, and the blood in the Veins, which uncorrupted is the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of Life and Health, but corrupted, is the cauſe of all diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, and muſt be purged, elſe the whole Body will periſh.</p>
            <p>The diſtempers from the Head or Heart are defuſive, and each Member feels its part: Hence comes the general complaint, all cry for eaſe, but few or none ſeek the right means of eaſe, but as ſick men deſire change, weary of every place, loath every wholſome thing, ſhift from pillow to pillow, from bed to bed, from one place to an other, ſtill the diſtemper grows: Then the Phyſitians are blamed, railed on, and reviled, becauſe they were deemed petty gods, able to cure all, but finding them but men, we'll not be adviſed by them, what they preſcribe for cure, the people reject, and what they tell us cheriſheth the diſeaſe, the people deſire; this (as to a perſon, ſo) to a body Politick, not onely prolongeth the cure, but increaſeth the diſtempers, all this cometh by the mutability in men.</p>
            <p>To ſpeak plain, the cauſe of the diſtempers in <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> is either in the King or People, or in King and People: The <hi>Eſſex</hi> men in their commanding Petition, implyedly lay the fault in the Kings abſence from His two Houſes of Parliament, ye all know His Majeſty withdrew Himſelf from them; yet thoſe Petitioners would vent their ſpleen againſt the Parliament, becauſe they do not Treat with His Majeſty Perſonally; as if a Treaty would change
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:115893:4"/>the Kings heart: but they forget their former complaints, and cryes under Royal burthens, arbitrary preſſure, that lay upon them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this Parliament began, becauſe (as I told you) mutation cauſeth oblivion; the other Countreys, <hi>Kent, Surry, Suſſex,</hi> &amp;c. in their ſedicious way ſeem to Petition for a Perſonal Treaty, or rather command it to he had, and fix Peace as the aym, to fool other Counties, as themſelves were fooled by the Enemy: but while Peace is in their mouthes, War was in their hearts and hands; their Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions ſpake Peace, but their aſſociation with arch Incendiaries and Delinquents, proclaimed War; this is evident, as their folly to be ſo fool'd, to act their own ruine by their own hands.</p>
            <p>For my part, I blame not any modeſt way of Petitioning, for it is the Peoples Intereſt, nor do I blame any of theſe Counties for Petitioning for a Treaty, I really believe a Treaty is the beſt way to ſettle the Kingdom; but I juſtly blame the uncivil way of Petition<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and abhor the practice of taking Arms againſt a Parliament: It is poſſible a Treaty may conclude all differences, but not very certain, yet it would be more advantagious to the Parliament then to the King; my Reaſon is, becauſe the People conceive the King will conſent to any thing that is right, and that He is now an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other man, will confirm Law, and ſecure the Subjects Liberty, &amp;c. it is the deſire of my heart that it may be ſo, for I truly honor the King: But if His Majeſty upon tryal ſhall refuſe to do what the people ſay he will do, and hath offered, or what ſhall be ſufficient to ſecure their Rights, it will then plainly appear to them, and to all the world where the fault is, and the hearts of the people will and muſt cleave to the Parliament for ſafety.</p>
            <p>But before there can be a Treaty, there muſt be ſome Security, elſe the Parliament (and with it) all good Subjects may be deſtroyed together; for if they that have been the Original of theſe bloody Wars, drew his Majeſty from his Parliament, and endeavored an Arbitrary Government, and Innovation of Religion, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured this War, ſtand ſtill in power (as we ſee they are able to raiſe a new War) be not brought to Juſt puniſhment, or ſome reſtraint laid on them, they will be incouraged to take advantage of a Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to do the ſame again and worſe: for except ſecurity be firſt given, they may change the Scene, from a Treaty to a Tragedy, but a Treaty is now reſolved on, as ſoon as it may be with conveniency
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:115893:4"/>and ſafety: no time nor endeavor is omitted, the people ſee it, and know it: Beſides, the King having formerly publiſhed ſeveral De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarations, and Proclamations, rendring the Parliament, and all that have adhered to them, to be Traytors, and Rebels; Thoſe Declarations and Proclamations muſt firſt be recall'd, elſe how ſhall the Parliament be in a fit capacity to Treat; but the Petitioners ſay not a word of this, nor ſo much as once mention their Solemn Covenant, which ſhews what kinde of Spirits they are of, and what is their deſign, nor are any to judge of this but onely the Parliament, what is ſafe, and what not. It is true, there have been obſtructions to Treaties and to Peace, but that was never the Parliament, but particular men that ſeek their own ends; to ſome ſuch we know War is Peace, and Peace will be their loſs: But we know great bodies move ſlow, and great buſineſſes cauſe long debates, and the Parliament have had a Brother Kingdom to joyn in all Treaties and Peace; a buſineſs once well done, is done for ever, but done to halfs, is worſe then undone, and will prove unrepairable prejudice to the publique; time, endeavor and patience will help all.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> The Parliament have had time enough, ſate many years, done nothing as to Settlement, either in Church or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monweal, but all things grow worſe, except to ſome that have ſought themſelves, and gotten eſtates out of others loſs; they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to have no King at all, Voted no more Addreſſes to be made to Him, but have kept up an Army to over rule the Kingdom, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>To this I anſwer, They have ſate long, and with great difficulty they have endured much, taken great pains, yet cannot effect that which we deſire; the Reaſon is, becauſe there are ſome joyned with them in the work, like <hi>Sheba,</hi> ſons of <hi>Bichri,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 20.1.</note> that would not have a King nor Peace; others like the revolted promiſcuous <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maritans,</hi> of <hi>Sanballats</hi> confederacy, adverſaries to Reformation, who under pretence of building Gods houſe, pull down what others endeavor to build; as in <hi>Ezra</hi> and <hi>Nehemiahs</hi> time, beſides the people of the Land (the great complainers) have (as then they did) <hi>Weakned their hands troubled them, yea,
<note place="margin">Ezr. 4.</note> hired Counſellors againſt them to fruſtrate their purpoſe;</hi> ſo that this Parliament have been forced to tread unknown paths, and met with unheard of op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions, as no Parliament of <hi>England</hi> ever did before them; then
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:115893:5"/>no marvel if the work be long: But to ſay, that things are worſe then they were, is a ſcandal: It is true, things are very ill, and much the worſe by the complainers calumnies, and ſeditious Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titions, thwarting one another: And whereas you ſay they have ſought themſelves, you muſt diſtinguiſh between the Parliament and particular men; that ſome men in Parliament have been meer ſelf-ſeekers, I with ſorrow of heart acknowledge, but the people ſent them thither, therefore the people that make no better choyce are in fault, not the Parliament; But why are the good deſpiſed? one mans fault doth not make another to be guilty, no more then <hi>Peter</hi> and the reſt of the eleven Apoſtles, were to be condemned becauſe <hi>Judas</hi> was alſo an Apoſtle, yet a Thief, a Traytor and a Devil: You ſay they intend to have no King, thats clearly falſe and injurious; Why then did the Parliament offer Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſals to the King ſo often from time to time? and really pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe to make His Majeſty greater then His Progenitors, if they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended not to eſtabliſh their King? Let but His Majeſty yet ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure the Kingdom, and I ſhall not need to ſay this Objection is falſe: That a Vote paſt the Houſe to make no more Addreſſes to the King is true, becauſe He might ſee (He refuſing their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſals) they intended to ſettle the Kingdom without Him; but that Vote was onely reſtrictive, <hi>No more Addreſſes without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of Parliament,</hi> yet as Parliament ſhould ſee cauſe, they might notwithſtanding that Vote, make as many Addreſſes as they would, but not perpetually, there muſt be an end of offering: In a word, whatever failing have been in actions or ſucceſs, it is not to be laid upon Parliament, but particular men and faction, private de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns and ſelf-intereſt. There have been factions and factious men, and that hath added to the Kingdoms miſery; Is it not ſo in all Societies? What City, Town or County in this Kingdom is free? and is the thing that threatens deſolation, pride and covetouſneſs is the cauſe of it; beſides Romaniſts, Epiſcopaliſts and Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines have broached ſtrange Opinions and old Hereſies, ſuch as have been condemned by the pureſt Primative Churches, and are contrary to Scripture, ſound Doctrine, and the power of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs: theſe have ſtrengthned factions; and factions have bred quarrels and ſidings, by which we have weakened our ſelves, and ſtrengthened the Enemy, and acted their deſign all along, ſo
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:115893:5"/>as we may truly ſay, if God give us to deſtruction, our deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is of our ſelves, and all this is Gods juſt judgement upon the Nation, <hi>Becauſe we received not the love of the truth,
<note place="margin">2 The. 2. Iſa. 19.14.</note> but had plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in unrighteouſneſs, therefore God ſent us ſtrong deluſions, that we might believe a lye,</hi> And mixed <hi>a perverſe Spirit in the midſt of us, cauſing us to erre.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And for your Objection, as to the keeping up the Army, I ſay, it is Gods great mercy that there is ſuch an Army on foot in the Kingdom at this day, they are the means under God by which we or any thing that is ours are preſerved, yet I will not juſtifie any thing not juſt in any; evil muſt not be done that good may come of it, yet God in his wiſe providence turneth evil to good; as the ſelling of <hi>Joſeph</hi> into <hi>Egypt</hi> was a wicked act in his brethren, but was the means (by Gods providence) of preſerving them and their old father from death: Surely no Army in all the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian world have been more proſperous, ſuceſsful and faithful, as to an Army, they have prevailed in all their attempts againſt the Enemy like <hi>Joſhua</hi> and <hi>Caleb,</hi> and deſerve honor and reward above ordinary Soldiers, notwithſtanding they be men of infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities as other men, <hi>In many things we offend all;</hi> How ſhall we look to be forgiven, if we will not forgive? or how can we for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give an Enemy, if we will not forgive a friend one treſpaſs? eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially ſuch a friend as hath delivered us, and doth deliver us from the wrath of a cruel Enemy.</p>
            <p>I have a word or two (by your patience) to whiſper to the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous City, <hi>London:</hi> I ſay famous City, for ſo ye once were, for your zeal to God, bounty to your friends, and gallantry againſt your Enemies; you were a terror to the Enemy, a comforter to your friends, a ſupporter to the Kingdom, and a refuge to the diſtreſſed that fled to you for ſhelter, your ſelves like <hi>Zebulun</hi> and <hi>Nepthtali, Were a people that jeoparded their lives in the high places of the field, To the help of the Lord againſt the mighty:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iudg. 5</note> Give me leave by way of complaint to ask you, How comes it to paſs that you are fallen back, revolted, loſt your firſt love, violated your Covenant, I ſpeak not to the Magiſtratical part of the City (who ſtill hold to their firſt principles) but to the generality of the inhabitants (eſpecially to the yonger ſort) who of friends are become Enemies: I have obſerved (but few take notice) that of late very many Delinquents have put their Sons Apprentice in this City; you may ſee their end by their practice. Conſider, I
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:115893:6"/>pray,
<note place="margin">Luke 9.62.</note> the ſaying of our Savior Chriſt, <hi>No man having put his hand to the plough, and looking back is fit for the Kingbom of God:</hi> Do not ye lightly eſteem the Rock of your Salvation; ye began well, why ſuffer you your ſelves to be ſeduced by the Enemy? ye did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the Cauſe to be juſt (and ſo indeed it was, as ever any war, as to the defenſive part) Errors in the managing, alters not the cauſe, nor can warrant your falling off: The quarrel is the ſame, the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my is the ſame, and your Intereſts are the ſame that they were at the firſt; How comes it then that ye are changed? Surely this is an evil change; you now make Leagues with the ſame Enemy againſt whom ye ſo lately were engaged, notwithſtanding the Enemy ſtill hates you, and ſeeks to deſtroy you: Nay, ye know the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my is Gods Enemy, and an Enemy to the Truth, and to your Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion and Liberties: Will you pull down what with ſo great diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty you have built up? Why do ye ſuffer Horſe to be at this day liſted in your City by that Enemy, and do not apprehend them that do it? You do not onely evil your ſelves, but you cauſe and encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage others to do like you: The eyes of the Kingdom are upon you, as formerly by your good example, many were forward to the help of the Lord againſt the mighty: ſo now by your evil ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample many draw back, and are ſeditious, yea, ſtrengthen the hands of the enemy, that they may be mighty again, and then they will deſtroy you: Was <hi>Meroz curſed becauſe they came not out to help the Lord againſt the mighty?</hi> and can <hi>London</hi> be bleſſed if they help the mighty againſt the Lord; yet <hi>Meroz</hi> was not engaged by any Covenant,
<note place="margin">Iſa. 30.1.</note> nor by ſo great an intereſt as <hi>London</hi> is: <hi>Wo unto the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious City, ſaith the Lord, that take counſel, but not of me, that cover with a covering, but not of my Spirit, that they may adde ſin unto ſin.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 1.21.</note> May it not be ſaid of <hi>London,</hi> as once of <hi>Jeruſalem, How is the faithful City become an Harlot? It was full of Judgement, Righteouſneſs lodged in it, but now murtherers; thy ſilver is become droſs, &amp;c.</hi> You that could not have endured to hear reproach in private againſt the Authority of Parliament, now are reproachers your ſelves, and joy to ſee and read baſe and ſcurrilous Pamphlets, and encourage them that vent them in your ſtreets, to all parts of the Kingdom. It cannot be but you muſt be brought into the refining furnace; ſhall God viſit the corrupted ſtreams, and not viſit the fountain that corrupteth? the ſword hath gone round through all Counties and Towns, and ſhall it eſcape <hi>London?</hi> it is not to be hoped, without there be a general Reformation, and a Humilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:115893:6"/>to divert it: If <hi>London</hi> drink the dregs of Gods wrath, it will be bitter, look to it, and look for it, ye that are ſecure in your ſins, and wiſh the Enemy may enter your ſtreets, you ſhall not eſcape when that day cometh, for God will finde you out, and make them that you account your friends to be your deſtroyers; remember therefore from whence ye are fallen, and to what you are changed, and do your firſt works.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Objection,</hi> We are the ſame we were, we are not changed, but the cauſe is not that it was; our firſt Engagement was for Defence of our Laws, our Religion, Priviledges of Parliament, and Liberty of the Subject, and withal, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the Perſon and Honor of the King in the preſervation of theſe; but our Laws are changed, our Religion loſt, Parliament forced to do and undo, our Liberties infringed, Trade diſcouraged and decayed, the King contemned, the Peace of the Kingdom re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarded, and we who have born the heat of the day, ſpent our blood and waſted our Eſtates, are now rejected as Malignants, becauſe an Army may not govern over our City, to force a change in our Religion and Government, &amp;c. all which is contrary to our firſt engagement, but is the deſign of the Army.</p>
            <p>For anſwer, you are not the ſame you were, though grant you (or many of you) have had diſcouragement; but the truth is, you are poiſoned in judgement by your frequent converſe with Delinquents, who works upon your diſcontents and jealouſies, and breed jealouſies to that end between you and the Army, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Presbyterian and the Independent, ſo as you dare not truſt one another, no not ſo much as a Chriſtian dare truſt a Turk; but upon meer jealouſie they have put you upon deſigns againſt the Army, and the Army upon revenge againſt you, neither juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiable among Chriſtians: Is this the way of God? or can men that are godly do ſuch things? theſe are fruits of ungodlineſs from City and Army: In a word, your Laws are not changed nor changing, but they are broken in pieces by both your diſobedience; your Religion is not loſt, but it is thruſt out of your Churches, as out of your houſes and affections, by your neglect of Duties, your prophanation of Sabbaths, contempt of Holineſs, and your ordinary practice of execrable Impieties, which is grown bold and audacious, impious in the ſight of God and men; ſo as to ſwear, to be drunk, to whore, to break the Sabbath, ſcoff at holy Faſts, revile Magiſtracy, to deride the Miniſters, and the very Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:115893:7"/>is to be ſecure; but to be obſerved, not to be one of them that do thus, or to reprove any their wicked practices is death, or threatning of ruine at the leaſt, is this to be as ye were? when ye durſt not be prophane, but fill'd your Churches on Sabbath days and Faſts days (not the Fields and Brothel houſes as now) You ſay the Parliament is forced, God forbid, though 'tis too true it hath been ſo, but by whom? I wiſh the City as well as the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my were not guilty of ſome forcings: Your Liberties are not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fringed, except you count that infringment, that you are reſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from deſtroying your ſelves and your poſterities: Nor is your Trading diſcouraged, but furthered by the Parliament; it is true, by your own diviſions you have cauſed Forrain Merchants to be jealous to truſt or trade with you at preſent: You know a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle before this Parliament begun, your Trade was diſcouraged and loſt, Who did that? (the Parliament redeem'd it) when all Trading was cut off by Monopolies, ſo as you all cryed out you were undone without remedy, when that projecting old Lord <hi>Goring</hi> was a more ſmoking Monopolizer then ere he was a Soldier, yet now you flie to ayd him, is not this a change? do you think to mend Trading by bringing in old Monopolizers; be ſure as you live they cannot live without their old trade, you do well to love them that hate you, but you ſhall finde they will grow rich, and make <hi>London</hi> poor; the eye of envy hath been upon you long, you have been thought too great to be ruled, now they will rule you if ye provide not againſt it, and make you as little as your yonger brethren: It may be the revolting of our Ships may prejudice your Trade a little, but that's your own faults, who have given ill examples, and diſcouragement to Land and Sea, it is the fruit of your own devices: That the Peace of the Kingdom hath been retarded, I deny not; I blame not the City, nor Parliament more then the Army, who were thought very faulty in that particular, <hi>I believe they have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented of it, and I hope God hath forgiven it, therefore I accuſe none;</hi> it is ſure we miſt time, it were well it were redeemed: But to your Objection, that you have born the heat of the day, and are now rejected, &amp;c. I ſay little, but wiſh thoſe that deſire peace to the Kingdom, to be at peace one with another; I know the Army were too high, and ſo were the City too: but let's be friends, it was bad in both, let's forget it: As to your Allegations againſt the Army, I muſt ſay, (and do ſo eſteem it) it is a very great mercy
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:115893:7"/>that God preſerved this Army againſt ſuch a time as this, when Men and Devils had combined to ſwallow us up at once, the deſign hath been Two years hatching, the ſolicitous Petitions for ſpeedy Disbanding of the Army, was one branch of it: The Enemy was confident of ſucceſs, nothing but the Lord <hi>Fairfax</hi> Army obſtruct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: Let <hi>England</hi> bleſs God, that the Lord <hi>Fairfax</hi> had now an Army ready; and that the Army, notwithſtanding ſo much diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement, ſo freely and gallantly adventured their deareſt lives to defend us: Be grateful to the Army, they are our defence, let them be ſtill owned for our Army, willingly, till the Enemy be ſecured; fear them not, they will not diſturb the Parliament, nor the City, but defend both, nor will they change Laws, nor tolerate Hereſie, nor awe the City, I (have fear'd it as others, but) now believe the contrary: poſſibly they may deſire a lawful moderation, between rigid penalty (to ſuch as are truly conſcientious) &amp; looſe Liberty in ſuch as hold unſound Doctrines, what they have done amiſs theyl do no more; <hi>Once have I ſpoken</hi> (ſaith holy <hi>Job</hi>) <hi>but will not anſwer, yea twice, but will not proceed any farther;</hi> This I ſay for the Army really.
<note place="margin">1 Sam. 15.22, Verſe 23.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Now give me leave, a word to the Army: <hi>To obey is better then the fat of Lambs;</hi> Obedience is to be preferred before Sacrifice, and <hi>Rebellion is as the ſin of witchcraft:</hi> Soldiers (though noble) are but Servants to them that imploy them, they are to defend them, and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend the Enemy; not to rule the Common-weal, nor ſettle the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of Chriſts Church, Chriſt hath appointed others for that office; nor will Jeſus Chriſt own ſuch a Government as ſhall be ſet up by Policy, juggling and carnal devices: God needs not mans lye, nor will he proſper that thing to a good man (though the thing be good in it ſelf) that is gotten by deceit. I pray tell me, if I ſhould tell you I am journeying into the North from <hi>London</hi> to <hi>Barwick,</hi> and you ſee me go forward in a way to the South, would you not be jealous that I meant not as I ſaid? Actions ſpeak better truths then proteſtations.</p>
            <p>I have alſo a word to ſay to my neighbor-counties, <hi>Kent, Eſſex, Suſſex, Surrey</hi> and <hi>Middleſex:</hi> I have ſeen your Names to a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration, and ſeveral Letters written to ſeveral Towns, Cities, and particular men in the North and Northweſt, perſwading upon your ſtrength and example, to Inſurrection, Treachery, and horrid Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience: But I hope it was not your own hands, nor with your hearts, but theirs, that have ſeduced you, fooled you, and in the nick of time, by your examples, would have ſeduced the whole King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom:
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:115893:8"/>I mean, old Courtiers, Monopolizers, Tobacco-men, and Cavaliers, who at this day by all kinde of fraud and force ſeek to make up an Army to deſtroy the kingdom, notwithſtanding they know a Treaty is reſolved on, and preparing with all ſpeed, both Honorable and Safe: But the kingdom, by Gods providence, have been wiſer then to deſtroy themſelves, as you have done; yet if any had been as bad as you, they might have had better plea for it then you; for, all parts of the kingdom have ſuffered much, you nothing; they have been plundred of all, driven from their habitations, lyen wallowing in their bloods, while you were in ſafety under the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments wing, injoyed your Trade, your rich crops, your lands fully ſtockt, you bought cheap and ſold dear, that ye grew rich, and <hi>were waxen fat,</hi> then <hi>like Jeſhurun, you kicked,</hi> againſt <hi>God,</hi> and your friends that fed you, aſſociated with your Enemies that would de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy you, and brought the Sword to your own doors, yea into your bowels: I pity your folly, and pray <hi>God</hi> you may be ſenſible of it, and be warned for after time.</p>
            <p>Now I would conclude my whole Meſſage to all honeſt Engliſh men, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther upon the Land or in Ships: Let not jealouſie grow among you, forget what is paſt, let not friends become Enemies, labor to be all of one minde and love one another, be gentle, courteous, peaceable, do good to all, do injury to none, joyn as one againſt the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon Enemy; pray to God earneſtly to change the Kings heart, and make the Parliament to agree in one minde, that God may accept both, and that there may be a happy compoſure of things between the King and his people, that he may inherit his throne with all Honor, and the people every one ſit under their own vine, in peace and content.</p>
            <p>In the mean time let none be ſo fooliſh, as to think by deſtroying the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, they can have the leaſt eaſe of any burthen, task, or other preſſure; for, if the King come upon ſuch terms, as to be brought in by an army of Cavaliers, your burthens will be greatly increaſed, for they will exact all ſums of money borrowed by the King, or by any for him, in any other Kingdoms; or what loſs any of their friends (ſo called) have ſuſtained, or what arrears are due to any of their Soldiers; and all that the Queen hath borrowed in <hi>France, Holland, Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark,</hi> &amp;c. muſt be made good out of your Eſtates: Beſides, your Freedoms &amp; Liberties will be loſt for ever, and a toleration of Popery muſt be of neceſſity granted, His Majeſty cannot deny that, they will have it; for therefore the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts in all parts ingaged in this War, and lent great ſums of mony, and owe vaſts ſums to the Catholicks beyond the Seas, all which you muſt pay: Nor ſhal you be able to help your ſelves, a continued army will be kept to awe you, the Subject muſt be diſarmed, and no ammunition to be had but by Ticket: Then will the people mourn, curſe themſelves, and tear their hair, when too late, without remedy; cry out of their miſery, and bewail their eternal Slavery brought upon themſelves, their children, and childrens children to laſting ages.</p>
            <p>I onely inminde you of theſe things, as <hi>Samuel</hi> did the people, when they impatiently asked a King, before Gods time was to give a King to them, he
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:115893:8"/>told them what they ſhould ſuffer; I do the ſame to you, not to diſſwade you from the King, but to perſwade you for your good, and the Kings ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, to ſtay Gods time; and in the interim beg a new heart of God for the King, ſuch as <hi>David</hi> had; God hath promiſed to give it. Supplicate the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament with all humility, ſpeak plainly (as to your Grievances) as free men, but honor and maintain the Priviledges of Parliament as your Freehold, your Eſtate, your Lives, for it is more to you then all; enthral not your ſelves, and God will not enthral you: He that hath been with you, will not forſake you, except you forſake him. Do not tempt God.</p>
            <p>God is doubtleſs working a wonderful work at this time in the world, greater then that of bringing <hi>Iſrael</hi> out of <hi>Egypt:</hi> God doth not ſhake the very foundations of Empires, Kingdoms, Cities and People for nothing, nor for any ſmall change in the world: Antichriſt is falling, he muſt fall, and will fall ſuddenly; The ſcattered <hi>Jews,</hi> now like vagabonds in all Nations, muſt be gathered together, and ſhall believe Ieſus Chriſt to be the true Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiah; There ſhall be but one Shepherd, and one Sheepfold; Some King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms and Nations muſt be conſumed to duſt, ſome muſt be purged in the fire of Afflictions; as fire tryeth ſilver, ſo variety of afflictions muſt try the Saints; but there muſt be <hi>a falling away firſt, and there muſt be Errors and Hereſies, that they that be approved may be made manifeſt;</hi> and that is in theſe days, and at this time: then God will <hi>put his Law into our hearts,</hi> and we ſhall all know God, and be of one minde, one heart, and one way; and in the end all oppoſers of Chriſt, and Reformation, all Papiſts, Atheiſts and Hereticks, all prophane Cavaliers, and looſe licencious men, that now rebel againſt God, the Magiſtrate, Law, Religion, &amp;c. ſhall all come to confuſion, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more ſure; they make Lyes their Refuge, and make a Covenant with Death, are at agreement with Hell, and ſay no hurt ſhall come to them; but the overflowing ſcourge ſhall ſweep away that Refuge, and they ſhall periſh ſuddenly; they for a time are Gods rods to afflict his people, though they exerciſe their own malice, rage and fury againſt Gods truth, and think to bury Reformation in the womb; <hi>They all combine, take counſel together, hold confederacies, and are aſſociated in power, yet they ſhall be broken in pieces; all their counſel ſhall be fruſtrate, their confederacy blaſted,
<note place="margin">Iſa. 8.9.</note> and their deſigns come to nought.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>If ye believe the Prophets, ye ſhall proſper; if ye will not believe the Prophets,
<note place="margin">2 Chr. 20.20. Iſa. 7.9.</note> ye ſhall not be eſtabliſhed.</hi> Suppoſe you ſhould ſee many thouſand dryed ſtraws march furiouſly againſt a burning coal, and compaſs it about, thinking to overwhelm it, and ſmother it, Whether will prevail, think you, at the laſt? Thoſe multitudes of ſtraws may for a time ecclipſe the light of the fire, but the heat will encreaſe, till at length it break forth into a flame, and will in a moment conſume them every one. Thus all wicked men, now com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bined-againſt God and Reformation in Doctrine and life (for thats the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward cauſe of all this hurly burly) though God may for a time ſuffer them, and himſelf by them, afflict men for their ſelf-ſeeking, and ſelf-aſcribing, and miſcarriages of buſineſſes, ſo as theſe men may ecclipſe the light of truth, yet it ſhall ſurely break out as a devouring flame, and conſume them all; <hi>It is hard to kick againſt pricks:</hi> Theſe are trying times, times for exerciſe of every grace in men, Faith, Hope, Patience, Humility, &amp;c.
<note place="margin">Hab. 2.4.</note> Graces would not be ſeen, nor known, nor ſhould be rewarded, but by the exerciſe of every one, <hi>The juſt ſhall live by his faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:115893:9"/>
            <p>There is a twofold life which men live by, There is the life of Senſe, and the life of Faith; The life of Senſe is meer Natural, ſuch was the lives of the beſt of Heathen men, and ſuch is the life of moſt in the world (called Chriſtians) that live but as heathen and publicans, as without God in the world; They look onely upon outward means and events, truſt to the arm of fleſh, when that fails they ſink, as men without hope: But the life of Faith is,
<note place="margin">Heb. 11.6.</note> 
               <hi>To believe that God is, and that he is a rewarder of them that diligently ſeek him;</hi> Faith ſees things that are not, and beholds things that are promiſed, as if they were; when all outward means fail by which they hoped for accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhment of the thing hoped for, they ſtill are the ſame; <hi>If the Figiree bloſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom not, nor fruit be in the Vine, the Olive fail, and the field yield no meat, though the flock be cut off from the fold, and there be no herd in the ſtall, yet they rejoyce in the Lord, and will truſt in the God of their Salvation;</hi> Faith makes not haſte, but ſtays Gods time, ſeeks no indirect means, reſiſts no workings of God, but traceth God in his footſteps, and obſerves the ſeveral turnings and wind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of Providences, is conſtant in duty, and leaves the Succeſs to God: If we would do thus, and lay aſide all by-ends, carnal policy, and hurtful jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, it would be well with us quickly.</p>
            <p>I wiſh I could perſwade men to their own good, to be patient, and to wait upon God, ſuffer God to work his own work in his own way, by his own means, in his own time, though he ſeem long, he will come ſuddenly, and none can hinder; for it is the work of God that is now in mens handling, not mans work: and when all outward means and hopes fail; and things ſeem to drive contrary to the thing we hoped, then is it neareſt to be done, that no fleſh may boaſt; all men ſhall clearly ſee and acknowledge God alone hath done it, although the horrid prophaneneſs of theſe times may bring ſweeping Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments upon men, Sword, Fire, Famine, Peſtilence, all which are threatned at this day, and effects of Gods anger for ſin; yet all the ſins of the times ſhall not hinder Gods work of Reformation, for he doth it not for mans righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, but for his own Names ſake; and he delivereth a people that they may be righteous, not beeauſe they are righteous.</p>
            <p>Now in the laſt place, it is the earneſt requeſt and deſire of my heart, That all good men will joyn with me, to make our humble and frequent ſupplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to God, and our earneſt Petitions to the Parliament for theſe enſuing particulars, which granted will amend all:</p>
            <p>Firſt, That God will make our hearts clean, and to truſt in God, ſeek his face, be obedient to Parliaments, ſubmit to all juſt commands, defend their Priviledges, and uphold them to all poſterity.</p>
            <p>Secondly, That all Members of Parliament may deny themſelves, ſeek Gods glory, bonor the King, ſtudy the Peoples Peace, and the happineſs of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, repent of their own ſins, covetouſneſs, oppreſſion, pride, exceſs, and the like, and become examples of piety by their own practice (becauſe example is more prevalent to teach then precept) Then, that they will freely and cordially paſs by all unkindeneſſes, and ſailing among themſelves, forget all, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give one another, abandon all jealouſies, be all of one minde, love as dear bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, endeavor to keep a conſtant full Houſe, maintain free Elections, free Debates, carried on by ſtrength of Reaſon, ſound judgement, and argued with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out prejudice, upon publique grounds, waying all ſelf-intereſt and by-ends. This ſhall ever be my Supplication, as many as will joyn with me ſhall par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take of the bleſſing by it: But if all ſhall refuſe me, thus He live, and thus He dye, and pray for the King and Parliament.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
